a very good evening to all our viewers
today today we have with us a very
special guest and a distinguished csr
professional he has worked from the
ground to the up helping
the government uh and reaching out all
the end beneficiaries in terms of
livelihood development they have reached
the far most uh areas the rule the most
rural areas in this country and uh
enabled a lot of women entrepreneurs a
lot of youngsters
unemployed youngsters to develop skills
and to gain jobs let us all welcome mr
saurabh saying president uh icici
foundation for inclusive growth welcome
on our show sora thank you
um
so uh sarah you have been with icsei
bank for more than two decades and
sculpted their csr work with icici
foundation how has your how has your
journey been
so i think uh my
voice is clear
yes yes yes
okay ah
let me clarify that uh i've been with
the organization for now
22 years but as a banker
out of that six years has been with the
foundation
so isis foundation was registered in
but it did pick up steam opposed the act
and
2014 onwards we picked up a lot of steam
as we went forward the profits grew in
the organization so the foundation also
picked up pace and
kept adding on activity after activity
if you
if i have to speak about myself
i was a was an hr professional
and uh i volunteered to move into
banking
so converted myself into a banking
professional
and uh
somewhere down the line i was given
additional uh charge of uh isis
foundation
six years back
and uh
some amount of background to it in the
sense uh
my father was a horticulturalist so i as
a kid i was always
i spend my childhood in agriculture
university campus
so familiarity with agriculture
come from agriculturalist family so
i mean we have our own farmland so again
familiarity with village and have kept
contact with
my own village
for the last
few decades so
there's been a fair amount of
understanding at a personal level
and being a banker anyway we service
the entire segment which is urban and
rural
so it gives a
overview of what's going on financially
in the country
and it does help being a banker
the overview which one gets about what's
happening in the economy
so
the ideas we get for development
we generally are able to correlate
a micro idea with what's going on in the
economy and then try and convert it into
something big
so the experience of uh
working at isis foundation
which is a part of a bank
i think is extremely lucky
and uh
extremely fulfilling
wonderful
uh so sort of recently uh
it's a remarkable journey i must say
uh from a banker to working in the
development uh profession
now uh recently we all faced core with
19 crisis which stalled most of the
ground activities
your foundation actually works a lot at
the grassroot
level how did y'all cope up with it and
what what were the technological tools
that you all use to reach out to the end
beneficiaries
this is really a very vast question i
think one can speak and speak on this
question
see first thing is uh
when kovid happened in india
parallelly the country was ready with
technology so the
digital connectivity across the country
was more or less in place some places
it's very good some places may be weaker
but at least the country was digitally
connected
so at least there was no loss of
voice connectivity
in most cases even the digital data
connectivity was also available
now every other time when there's been a
crisis
this kind of a connectivity was not
available so definitely this crisis had
one advantage which was in terms of
digital connectivity
what failed if we really look at it that
there was scare
people were scared for their lives for
their safety
and
they chose to operate in their comfort
zones
so the people operating in urban india
some of them decided to migrate back
home and people were operating in rural
india
decided to stay home and not venture out
unless until it was very necessary
so if we
really analyze what was happening around
us
the entire
structured value chains were functioning
very well
the unstructured value chains which
on which the rural india depends
started failing
and for a value chain in rural india to
fail
even a few truck drivers decide to stay
at home
that's good enough for the value chain
to fail
forget the crowded mondays and all
if a few traders decide to stay at home
the trade in the monday will go down
and what exactly happened
for those of us who are staying in urban
india paid a higher price for the
produce
and the producers who are paying and
staying in rural india
were getting lesser money for their
produce
and
if we correlate with what is that one
irony
the indian farmer or indian rural
producer faces the biggest irony is
after two and a half months or three
months of a crop
i don't know
what will be my earning
on the day when i want to sell
what price will prevail in the market
whether i'll make a profit or a loss i
don't know
for everyone else people like us if we
work for 30 days we get a salary
the others
in
urban businesses where they decide what
profitability they want
but farmer is one community
comprising of almost
60 65 percent of our population
where they don't know
what profit they'll be able to make
and in such a scenario when the supply
chain starts failing
they had a tough time
now
it was very difficult to reach out to
them
but wherever we could we tried to form
informal supply chains
we tried to put up supply chains so that
certain housing societies start
receiving supplies
from a particular set of farmers
and
to do all this you needed enterprise
so the villages where
some people were enterprising enough
so we succeeded there were villages
where we could not find such
enterprising people
so we could not move ahead because
end of it you are dependent on
the desires of people who are involved
in the value chain
so some people some places we are
definitely
able to help out
and the orders would go digitally so we
developed small apps
and
even websites for a few where people
would place their orders and the
delivery package would come in
vegetables packed would come
now that helped them with their
livelihood in that tough period
second part what we tried to do whatever
funds we had
we did not stop our projects
we kept our projects rolling
despite inefficiencies because we knew
that
cash is again a commodity which is in
short supply in rural india which they
need
now if you're talking of technology
specifically
i'd be very frank i think cell phone was
the one technology which works in rural
india
and cell phone cell phone connectivity
is what we used
and
we helped develop a few apps
in a two two-week period three-week
period
which
the farmers were using to sell their
produce
so that was the real use of technology
and the cell phone was a
boon in disguise for the farmers at this
point of time
uh
that
we should all
thank to the amazing mobile connectivity
that we have so that we could reach out
to large number of people
uh
so that that's pretty innovative ways
that you all have found out to uh reach
out at the grassroot level
now uh when you are when we are talking
about financial inclusion
you are a csr arm of a bank
uh
and uh you have
worked extensively on financial
inclusion programs covering more than 12
lakh
and beneficiaries in 27 cities
what are the challenges that you find in
financial inclusion in spite of we
having the mobile technology and the
patients and all the possible
gateways available at our disposal
see the first and foremost problem i'll
say is
what
every educationist
faces in a classroom
that
the teacher comes with a
brilliant intent
comes prepared to teach
but then it's up to the learner
how much of learning they'll take away
or they will not take away
so the gap between
the trainers intent and the learner's
intent
is always
something which needs
a lot of bridging
classroom teaching and training is far
more structured because
you have a stream of students
who have volunteered to come there
when we are talking of financial
literacy
we go and approach all segments and all
sec
kinds of people across the country
and
small things like uh
i mean you go to go to any village
you have people with
large land holdings then you have the
medium land holdings the marginal
farmers and then you have the landless
at no point of time you can talk to them
together because their needs are very
different
even if you take urban areas
the people deployed in various kinds of
professions
doing various kinds of activities
and
we are talking of money
now money for a person who learned how
to manage surplus is very different
from a person
for whom the money is still just good
enough for consumption
so from consumption to get into a habit
of saving even saving five rupees per
day
is something which is a
remarkable change in life
i don't know how many of you have
visited rural india
there are several households in rural
india
where you won't find any storage
the clothes are hung on the wall
and you don't get to see storage spaces
and whatever gets earned is for
consumption
now in such a scenario you have to go
and tell that their banks are willing to
help you out
the first feeling is that bank is here
to take away my money
why should i trust the bank
when i go to the bank i have to stand in
a queue to deposit when i have to go to
withdraw my money i can have to stand in
a queue to withdraw
and
there'll be holidays there'll be working
hours
so why do i hand over my preciously
earned money
to a bank
so bringing about a change
so this is a very basic
and when we start working with them
convincing them
that small savings
will come in handy someday
then you are we understand that there's
a very big difference between the way
urban economy works and the way rural
economy works
the main differentiator is in urban
economy
we make we earn our money
and then spend
in rural economy people spend
and then earn and pay back the
money lender or the shopkeeper
so the entire money cycle is very
different
and to break that money cycle you need
change in mindsets
and when you are working on changing
mindsets you have a competitor there is
in the form of money lender
whose livelihood is threatened if the
mindset changes
so it's not easy to train people
of the lower strata on financial
inclusion it's far easier to teach a
lower middle class or middle class on
financial inclusion and various
instruments
but when it comes
to
train the bottom of the mermaid
it's very difficult you want to train a
person into becoming entrepreneur
it's so difficult to teach savings
and for an entrepreneur they need to
differentiate between what is capital
and what is revenue
now how do you train them
thousands of growth has been spent on an
entrepreneurship program
but
for bottom of the pyramid to learn the
difference between capital and revenue
is so difficult
and though that two percent or three
percent who learn
are the people who are able to
differentiate
so it's a very difficult one
but
efforts have to be made because one
cannot leave them where they are
they have to
come and be part of the society which is
uh
doing better which has a better per
capita
and it's in our interest that
we have financial inclusion
so that they form they feel part of it
they feel as part of the same society
that and because of the communication
that they're receiving through
television channels through mobile
phones they have access to everything
that urban indian has
so the exposure is very high
but
the capability and skill to manage money
is very low
so this divide and the gap is very high
and currently it's in it's a disturbing
trend
so more and more effort is required in
this area
to bring in financial inclusivity in the
country
i agree and i believe that you all are
doing uh tremendous work
to make it happen
now apart from the financial inclusion
livelihood generation by skilling is one
of the key initiatives by the icici
foundation
and there are a good number of success
stories that i see on your website now
also you all are you all have excelled
in placing the students on the
trade that uh they are being trained
uh in spite of all the successes there
are still many districts in india that
have educated unemployed you
where do you think is a gap and how do
you think we could bridge this gap
see there are various kinds of
initiatives that we are running
we are running an urban initiative where
we
have physical skill training centers
where we train the urban are unemployed
and help them with employment
in the last seven years we have placed
about
almost two lakh people now
in the rural areas we work with
the landless or with the marginal
farmers and try and enhance their income
so we work on the livelihood program and
we also work on the skills for
employment so skills for livelihood and
skills for employment are the two
distinct
programs we run
and we have been successfully running it
for more than seven years now
and the various experiences
so when we are talking of
skilling for employment
actually the choice is made by the kid
the kid who's coming for the program
decides end of the program whether they
want to get into employment or don't
want to get into employment
even if you get them a job
later after 15 days or
two months you find them again
unemployed and back
so
unfortunately
some definitions which operate in the
marketplace there's nothing which a
foundation can do
so for many people employment means a
government job
so if it's a private sector job
they don't count it as employment
so that's something maybe a
bridge employment or intermittent
employment and they don't value
it and at the same time there are others
70 uh attending the program who value it
so we have to deal with both these kind
of people
and similar
things we face in rural india
when you are skilling people
there are people who are
keen learners
they are keen experimenters and then you
also have a segment which is
generally around
listening to you
will not implement will not experiment
and end of the day
is happy where they are
so
working with any of these programs
it never works as the formula
but
the efforts we make
on trying to convince them and trying to
build their careers
let's take for example farming
majority of the country is employed
in that profession
agriculture as a profession
where are the trainers and who who is
training them to be a farmer
we are our productivities are lower
because we are running the age-old
practices of farming
there are
better
residue free farming
lesser use of chemical
better productivity is possible
and whatever techniques are there of
soil testing or water management
most of the things they are blissfully
unaware
and
the knowledge resides somewhere
so it's not that the knowledge doesn't
exist in the country the knowledge
exists
but
the actual producers do not receive this
knowledge
so that gap needs to be based in rural
india
to make our agriculture more robust
and
then
we also need to work on supply chain so
there are
those enterprising people staying in the
same area
who have the streak of enterprise
they need to be supported
to develop some enterprise which will
help the rest of the village
so in some cases
self-help group
or
informal communities also are able to do
but in many cases the individuals who
are able to
build uh
or rather enhance the economy of a
village and i'll just
give an example to prove my point
that
for any
rural supply chain
to succeed
on one side there has to be production
but on the other side there has to be
sale
now between production and sale if there
is a
there is a bridge the bridge can be
multiple traders could be one trader
but that bridge has to be robust
that's when the value of the produce
comes to the village
and
that bridge can be in the form of a
self-help group can be in the form of
fpo or can be in the form of individual
entrepreneurs
either is fine
there is no one success formula what has
succeeded in one village
may not succeed in another village
because the
nature the social structure
everything differs from village to
village
so we have to see every village as a
micro unit
and
develop enterprise around the village
which will help the village produce
reach the market place
and get sold in a proper manner and that
means
skilling from production
to managing supply chain in some cases
managing packaging some cases grading
and sorting
so depending on what they are producing
an intervention is required to add 20 25
value to the produce they have
in some cases could be
short duration storage
requirement
so far we have done almost
30 different kind of interventions
in different villages just to add value
to the produce so in some cases we may
have put up a
dal processing unit in some cases just
grading and sorting unit for
grains
in some cases we put a paneer processing
unit in some cases we produced a
installed solar koa making unit
or simply a
milk collection center
so
in total so far we have uh
promoted 260 such enterprise
which are helping villagers
to market their produce well
and we have trained them in the skills
of
processing
so
from
better quality agriculture to residue
free agriculture
to
semi-processing of processing that
produce to make it marketable at a
better price
so the entire value chain we work
and
it will take a duration of good three to
five years per village
to make the marketable and to enhance
the
cash flow of the village
okay
uh
that's a humongous task in front of you
to be honest
now you are a pioneer in csr
and esg investing is a upcoming term and
a new term in the process to get
mandated in india too
now the s of esg is still vague which
social causes in india can we include in
the generic level to ensure inclusive
growth at large
we are one of the largest populated uh
country in the world
and
i'll say purely from my experience
if we are able to empower the women
that will make the difference
so the yes in my mind
have to
be working with the women
i don't know how many people are aware
about this
that if you go to any village any
village in the country
majority population is women
because the men have left the villages
gone out to work to make money
so
if them if the male population is there
they
every village is actually a cluster of
women
so if we're working with women
at a village level and enhance their
cash income
we see the difference
the qual
the attendance at school goes up
the health care improves
nutrition improves
so when a
lady of the house earns more cash
we see lot of development happening
inside the household
and when the men
make more money
there are multiple other areas where
there are distractions and it gets spent
so
if there's one unit where
we would want to focus
it's working with the rural women
wonderful
that is really encouraging to
see now as as you rightly mentioned
icici foundation has been empowering a
lot of women by skilling and
entrepreneurship
still gender diversities
is at a back foot of the governing
council and the team in the time to come
would we see a change
governing council is the
group of ceos
so
every border board of director of that
organization decides who's the ceo of a
group company
so
foundation has no role to play in
who my dad will be
so those are the ceos of group companies
they sit in the governing council
and as far as
the foundation is concerned
team see
we come from a dna of icsa wherein
we have never been told to differentiate
i've had lady bosses for ages
so
the thought also doesn't occur to us
when you ask the question it occurred
that yes probably the
ratio of
men to women in the
leadership levels
is different right now at one point of
time it was very high currently it's
different
and if i look below
then i see a lot of
girls already working
so i think
the various points of time various
profiles of work
and personal preferences exercised by
people
so i mean
why teaching has so many women
why human resources has so many women i
don't think so anybody has done it by
design
it's a personal choice exercise by
people
and
there are foundations which have a lot
of women their foundation like us which
have
lesser women
so when i think of it
happy
is there a bias in selection i don't
think so
there's no bias in selection
is the number of people who'd be willing
to go amen
just now i was
reviewing something which is
a two-member team has been roaming
around in ladakh for the last four days
around the
lac villages
now
one of them is a lady
but
to be very frank i find very few
ladies who are willing to
work in such hard tough terrains
and to go to villages which are some
300 400 kilometers away from an airport
so it's not an easy job if i'm working
in balgar around mumbai then everyone is
willing because you go in the morning
and come back in the evening
but if i'm working somewhere in
marathwada
you necessarily have to go be out for
three days and you don't have best of
the hotels
out there
so csr is a tougher job
than an office job
and
if there are people who are willing to
come in
they're absolutely most welcome i don't
think so there's any bias
okay sir but i hope to see them also in
the leadership positions in the times to
come
uh
uh my other question do you all
collaborate with the grassroot level
ngos we have one of our viewers mr vijay
kamley also
asking if your foundation could work
with the pillar group in the field of
financial literacy
so
do you all collaborate with other
stakeholders
yeah we have a few collaborations with
other foundations other corporate
foundations wherein
they are doing their part of work we do
our part of work and if you see the new
guidelines of
mca they're very particular about the
projects and
the impact of the project so
it's best to keep it separate
but together
can we work with other foundations
wherein they are doing some work and in
the area where they have done probably
rural development can isis foundation do
financial inclusion my answer is yes
or if they're doing on certain things
can financial uh can i say the
foundation
add in value and whatever expertise we
have again my answer is yes
the next uh the previous question you
asked was on
partnering with ngos
i think we are very careful
we have had very bad experiences
and
again on the impact study that
we've spent growth and crores and
the promised impact and the actual
impact we could not see correlation
so we're very careful on that so other
ngos working with icsr foundation the
answer is yes
are they selective yes
they have been selected through a very
stringent and uh
process wherein we're very careful that
the money that we spent goes for the
right cause
and the impact
is known at any point of time and every
point of time
it's not easy to work with icf
foundation let me say that
okay
uh now iicsr is a dedicated institute to
develop responsible business leaders in
india which subjects do you think that
we should conduct for the work posed
from the ground up
executives managers and the board or the
cxo level
see i would say from personal experience
a lot of theory is known to everybody
and uh
there's no shortage of passion and
feelings that you want to bring about a
change
but when you want to be a change agent
it's very
important to understand
the social
structure of the
country
and how these social structures have an
impact
on the decision-making of the society
how it has an impact on rural
development and rural economics
so
the
sociology as a subject is very important
understanding india
from
social structures
and understanding the rural economics
end of it what are we trying to do
if we are trying to develop rural india
means
we want to improve the cash flow of
a particular village
to improve the cash flow
you have to get into commerce
and
that's what is
missing in most cases
so
unless until we have good understanding
of rural economics
and rural sociology
it's very difficult to work because
there are
complexities where
you cannot get the
entire village at one place at any point
of time
the certain segments certain parts of
the village which will respond to you
students will say
i'll respond if those people are not
there
then there are political compulsions so
that also needs to be understood
so
understanding
the
rural dynamics of the rural society
which i don't find
available in many textbooks
whatever
sociology i've read
i don't find it very well explained
and also the rural economics of india
and the rural economy differs from
state to state the theories will be same
but
the implications are very different
so these two subjects actually are the
foundation stone to success of a
development professional
or a esg professional
that's something we need to develop as
curriculum
to a level where we have researchers at
any point of time
india should be having at least 500
researchers working on this area
which i don't find
and let me also tell you
about five years back i attempted
contacting several educational
institutions
that
you would want to sponsor research
the moment you use the word sponsor
there are quotes coming in terms of
crores
how crores are required
to do any kind of research
so while they they're not doing anything
you want to bring them into research
then the greed comes in
so somewhere this gap
isn't getting fulfilled
and i would blame the
educationist for that because i made
attempt
several attempts to
build this knowledge by sponsoring but
i've been failing
so when i visit to bombay i'll
definitely come down to see you let us
discuss on this we we would be happy to
take up this initiative uh this being
our core competency we would be glad to
take this up and you wouldn't receive
budgets of cross we'll be more grounded
on this note i would like to invite dr
hopkins uh he has a
few questions for you dr hopkins over to
you
hi thank you uh can you hear me okay
yeah
okay excellent um very nice to meet you
sir and very impressive
your work thank you very much uh
i have two rather trivial questions for
you which you'll easily answer
but they're some of the toughest
questions to answer
my first question was is essentially
how as a banker
do you with your experience assess
projects that you look at
so
as you can imagine
how do you look at their viability what
what sorts of things do you look at in
terms of is it cash flow is it is it
education is it market
um so
from a banker's perspective with all
your experience my first question
and my second question is
um
probably a little bit also complicated
how do you assess
uh and you talk
in your introduction about skills in
your institute how do you assess what
skills are needed
um in a project or in an area and how do
you deliver
such skills
so very easy to ask ask the questions
but not quite as easy to answer um so
but um i i speak with my ilo i'm former
ilo hat on
and of course one of the biggest issues
in the world to stimulate growth and um
better income distribution
income distribution
is uh is skill development
and how should that be done through
institutions or on the job short term
long term and and so on
you also raise an interesting question
about women but
maybe if we've got time i'll come on to
that one as well but i think you've got
enough to chew on there but thank you
very much so the first question on as a
banker how do you assess projects and
two
how do you assess what skills are needed
in the projects
that you work on
so uh
my first response will be that
when you're working with uh
in a developed country and when you're
working in a developing country
the
entire uh evaluation framework
is very different
and
where i'm coming from is uh
in a developing nation there's so much
to be done
so much to be done that whatever
resources you have
is very
small and limited
so any area you pick up
as a project there is a need to work
so
it's a
case of plentiful projects being chased
by
very little amount of serious harmony
so that's the case of india now
as a bank what we would do
to be very frank we have chosen a
shortcut
and the shortcut is uh
we like one of the
failed policies of
ministry of rural development government
of india
wherein they had set up one skill
development sorry entrepreneurship
development
in every district
and
responsibility of running it was handed
over to a bank
for some reason two of those
were run by ictsa bank
and before getting into a strategy i had
visited those centers
and i love the model
so people who conceptualized the model
were definitely great thinkers and had
thought through
that this is something
if implemented it's called
rct
rural self-employment training institute
and every district in india has one of
them
now conceptually excellent
and it has it defines
a list of some 170 skills which can be
imparted they have a list of more than
10 000 trainers which are available
and
they also define that
there has to be a enhancement of
financial cash income every
month as a target
now very simply we picked up this model
and
we have
spread it amongst all our employees
which is 600 employees in the icc
foundation
and all of us talk the same language
that we when we enter
any any part of india
we have to enhance their income
and to enhance their income it could be
by skilling
or by some other interventions
but skilling being one of the core
interventions by which
we try to enhance the income
and
so far our experiences
by
spending about 10 000 rupees a month
sorry 10 000 rupees on a trainee
we are able to multiply their cash
income
anything
three times of this ten thousand to
six times
so an investment of ten thousand gives
them a sustainable income of between
thirty thousand to sixty thousand
and that makes a difference
to a rural household
so when i've gone ahead and calculated
the income and expense of a rural
household
by whatever
grains and supplies which come from
government
if the lady of the house
gets 5000
as cash income per month
then there are no cases of
malnutrition
or the student or the kids not going to
school
so that 5000 is a very critical number
and in rural india
there are very little expenses
the main expense cash outflow is the
cell phone which is about 300 rupees
a month
apart from that
they're buying
the monthly supplies which costs about
1200 to 1500 a month
so even with a 2000 cash income they're
at a sustainable level because the
grains are available either from their
own farmland or from the
public distribution system
so that's where we chose that if we make
it 5000 then they have a surplus income
and what we observed the moment the
incomes have
reached 5000 across 5000 the households
have bought television
the
dresses have improved
hygiene has improved
we've seen remarkable improvement in the
lifestyle of these people so at the
moment we are talking of a base income
now are there people who have
made it much better
one of cases who are making much more
money and their lifestyle has changed
that's different but
as such for the masses currently we are
targeting 5000 per month
and that's inspired by ministry of rural
development scheme which was
not functioning
so we've
received recognition from ministry of
rural development
for initiating this
and
the two
are cities we run one in udaipur and one
is jodhpur
have now been declared as model our
cities
and
it's been shown to others that this is
how
one can run a very successful model
uh coming to your second question on
skills
uh
i keep complaining on
what you said
that
india is a country there is no
forecast available
of any kind of skill
requirement in future
and we have a national skill development
corporation and i keep
requesting them
that if you can do this this would be
the biggest service to the nation
and
when i visited singapore i was
pleasantly surprised that they have a
model and they forecast what are the
skills required
in india i think we simply depend that
we have a
large population and
whatever needs to be done we have a lot
of people and
they're always willing to do
so i think
as a nation we have never
respected skills
we have
always
respected education
and
i don't want to sound negative but that
comes from the social structure which
existed for
centuries in this country
that promoted
education in a bigger way that gave
respect to
so education is aspirational skill is
not aspirational
and when we work with skills
we face this problem that it's not
aspirational despite our telling that
you'll earn
equal or more
as a skilled individual
people are not willing to believe
or
or they
want to
get a white collar job over a
blue collar skill
so
there's no forecast of any kind for any
profession so i'm a banker
and
if i have to forecast how many bankers
will be required next year i don't think
so there is any kind of a forecast
available
so this demand and supply
gap and
temporary management and long-term
management
each individual organizations do it for
themselves and as i see csi bank
the hr
division of icsf bank does forecast and
does try to manage the supply and demand
for our organization
but
i don't think so any industry in india
is even conscious about it because we
have so many people at any point of time
you want people you can get
so that's the most easily available
commodity in india
sad to say but that's the truth
interesting your comment on on on
singapore which has been a model
for
many
many countries around the world
used to be called the asian tigers you
remember maybe 20 30 years ago
with a massive investment in skills and
singapore is taking us pretty far um i
think linked to the german model as well
of skill development um which i'm sure
you you you know about um i i'm
generally in favor of uh of short
courses not not these rather long ones
which and these big institutes that
people people build
quite often
a skill
can be imparted
for example
baking bread for example
pretty pretty quickly and
and received uh with we with great joy
then the question is you know how do you
reproduce that and how do you uh make
many loaves of bread rather than one and
that's the
process that you were talking about in
your in your speech so i'm i'm pretty
impressed that you're you're right on on
top of all these things and
i think lucky india to have somebody
like you pushing all that all that
forward
with it with your experience and also
you've
eaten tandoori roti
sorry
you have eaten indian food the
tandoori roti
i love indian food
i wouldn't say i cook it so well but i
love it
i need some skill training there
[Laughter]
let me tell you the small story yeah
i built a farmhouse and i bought a
tandoor
and
neither my cook nor i
knew how to
make a tandoori roti
and
then i was discussing with my cook
that how did that expert learn learn to
do it
he must have tried it 200 times
so
let's google it how to do it
and
let's be ready that we'll waste 50 rotis
today
and trust me
the fifth one was in order
and by the time he made the 10th
he had become an expert
without a teacher
i did not know how i still don't know
how to do it
but i could make him do it just by
experimenting
well if you at first you don't succeed
you know the old adage try try and try
again
you know you you mentioned a number of
issues actually i don't want to dominate
this talk here but uh you mentioned
about about women um which was it was
quite interesting that process that's
going on you also mentioned the concept
of basic income which so happens my my
best friend is the father of that across
the world
um we can have a chat about that but how
should have to organize another meeting
to do that
so harsha thank you very much for
feeding me in for this talk anyway thank
you thank you dr hopkins for joining us
thank you pleasure
pleasure interacting with you thank you
i'd like to invite dr baddhai for asking
his next question so over to you
thank you
sorry it's always pleasure to listen to
you
the way you have modeled
a csr in your organization
uh it's a lesson to learn
but also lately we have been talking a
lot about what government is doing
i talk to a lot of csrs and all
like
we are getting more compliance we are
told that now work in health and all
especially with the public sector units
my question to you as a thought leader
and as a leading professional in csr
what should government do now and what
should be their varieties
see
my
my thought on this
is
[Music]
quite simple
the intent of
bringing introducing csr in the country
was brilliant
but
with intent everything does not happen
so there are institutions which are
doing wonderful job
and then there are institutions
which are not doing anything
and then there are institutions which
are
doing things with self-interest
so all kinds of practices are prevalent
around us
and
let's just take
examples of
that there are institutions which have
not even spent
[Music]
one percent of the money they were
supposed to spend
yes then there are institutions
let's take one example that
i am a family run concern
i build schools
so i've moved csr money for school
the trustees of the school are family
members
now
is it that the organization's wealth has
moved as family wealth
or is it csi
yes
right there are several unanswered
questions around us
i don't want to comment right or wrong
these are very tough answers
and
some amount of
i think
one attempt i like is bring about every
project in the open
let it be
seen by public so every project that's
happening we have to now submit as a
list
it's tiresome
but it's good that
it's in the public domain
that what kind of a project every
organization is doing and who the
beneficiaries are
so some amount of transparency will
bring in about self-consciousness in
organizations because regulations cannot
and we have seen there's so many laws
till crime happens so
it has to be saved
talk to you some other times always
pleasure to listen to you wherever you
are there i always listen to you
thank you sir thank you thank you
uh so we have few questions from uh
viewers on linkedin and other social
media group mr rajesh
asking a great work
uh youth a major source of
transformation of communities do you
have any more work in digital technology
related work for rural india
he runs a company known as connect which
connects the organizations
in the skills development
if we would like to answer the same
first let me
speak on the digital connect
we as foundation
are very conscious that
for rural india to improve
and for their economic development
the rural connect the digital connect is
very important
so
i would slightly take it bigger that
all kinds of technology
to be made affordable
and at a price which the farmers can
afford has to reach rural india
now as a bank or as a foundation
probably we will find it difficult so
what we are initiating now
is we are going to work on
promoting startups
of this nature
who are working on
digital technology for rural india
and we are launching a structured
program towards this
and few educational institutions of
eminence are involved with us so it will
be in collaboration
funded by icsa foundation
so very soon you will hear the launch
wherein we are going to have incubation
centers and
also we are willing to invest in some
technologies which we feel
has a long-term benefit to the farming
community
or the rural supply chain
thank you for answering that question a
few other compliments from you from mr
sriram singh from mr vijay kamle
and others who are our viewers uh any
final message to all our viewers and
students that you would like to mention
i think that they be able to achieve
uh the dream of a father of nation
village
so the day
these villages
become empowered and
these rural economies
become sustainable
see let's not forget that urban centers
came up because the rural surplus needed
a place to be traded
and now urban surplus has started
funding rural economy so the cycle has
changed
so
one imbalance the second imbalance
somewhere we need
a somewhat balance
never a stage in life when balance
happens
but
uh rural economy to become
self-resilient and
is the thought we have
and i would request everyone whatever we
can do in our ability i think we should
do
to contribute towards this achievement
thank you thank you thank you so much
it's a very profound message for all of
us thank you so much for joining us
saurabh it means a lot to all of us
and i'll bring all the present people in
the studio also to join us
so uh thank you everyone for joining
today it's been a wonderful
weekend evening thank you
thank you so much
thank you